<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2581 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2581.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc3649 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3649.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc='yes' ?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes' ?>
<?rfc sortrefs='no'?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<!-- <?rfc-ext parse-xml-in-artwork='yes' ?> -->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?> -->
<rfc docName="draft-sridharan-tcpm-ctcp-03" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev='CTCP'>Compound TCP: A New TCP Congestion Control for High-Speed and Long Distance Networks</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Bensley' fullname='Stephen Bensley'>
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
          <city>Redmond</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98052</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 425 703 5570</phone>
        <email>sbens@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Sridharan' fullname='Murari Sridharan'>
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <phone>+1 425 703 5438</phone>
        <email>muraris@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='K.' surname='Tan' fullname='Kun Tan'>
      <organization>Microsoft Research</organization>
      <address>
        <phone>+86 10 59173120 </phone>
        <email>kuntan@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='D.' surname='Bansal' fullname='Deepak Bansal'>
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <phone>+1 425 703 4789</phone>
        <email>dbansal@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='D.' surname='Thaler' fullname='Dave Thaler'>
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <phone>+1 425 703 8835</phone>
        <email>dthaler@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year='2014' />
    <area>Transport</area>
    <keyword>TCP</keyword>
    <keyword>CTCP</keyword>
    <keyword>congestion control</keyword>
    <abstract>
       <t> Compound TCP (CTCP) is a modification to TCP's congestion control  mechanism for use with TCP connections with large
       congestion windows.  This document describes the Compound TCP algorithm in detail, and solicits experimentation and
       feedback from the wider community.  The key idea behind CTCP is to add a scalable delay-based component to the standard
       TCP's loss-based congestion control. The sending rate of CTCP is controlled by both loss and delay components. The
       delay-based component has a scalable window increasing rule that not only efficiently uses the link capacity, but on
       sensing queue build up, proactively reduces the sending rate.  
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title='Introduction'>
      <t> In this document, we collectively refer to any TCP congestion control  
          algorithm that employs a linear increase function for congestion  
          control, including TCP Reno and all its variants as Standard TCP.  This  
          document describes Compound TCP, a modification to TCP's congestion  
          control mechanism for fast, long-distance networks. The standard TCP  
          congestion avoidance algorithm employs an additive increase and  
          multiplicative decrease (AIMD) scheme, which employs a conservative  
          linear growth function for increasing the congestion window and  
          multiplicative decrease function on encountering a loss. For a high- 
          speed and long delay network, it takes standard TCP an unreasonably  
          long time to recover the sending rate after a single loss event <xref target="RFC2581"/>, <xref target="RFC3649"/>.
          Moreover, it is well-known now that in a steady- 
          state environment, with a packet loss rate of p, the current standard  
          TCP's average congestion window is inversely proportional to the square  
          root of the packet loss rate [RFC2581,PADHYE]. Therefore, it requires  
          an extremely small packet loss rate to sustain a large window. As an  
          example, Floyd et al. [RFC3649], pointed out that on a 10Gbps link  
          with 100ms delay, it will roughly take one hour for a standard TCP flow  
          to fully utilize the link capacity, if no packet is lost or corrupted.  
          This one hour error-free transmission requires a packet loss rate of  
          around 10^-11 with 1500-byte size packets (one packet loss over 
          2,600,000,000 packet transmission!), which is not practical in today's  
          networks.  
      </t>
      <t> There are several proposals to address this fundamental limitation of  
          TCP. One straightforward way to overcome this limitation is to modify  
          TCP's increase/decrease rule in its congestion avoidance stage. More  
          specifically, in the absence of packet loss, the sender increases  
          congestion window more quickly and decreases it more gently upon a  
          packet loss. In a mixed network environment, the aggressive behavior of  
          such an approach may severely degrade the performance of regular TCP  
          flows whenever the network path is already highly utilized. When an  
          aggressive high-speed variant flow traverses the bottleneck link with  
          other standard TCP flows, it may increase its own share of bandwidth by  
          reducing the throughput of other competing TCP flows. As a result, the  
          aggressive variants will cause much more self-induced packet losses on  
          bottleneck links, and push back the throughput of the regular TCP  
          flows.  
      </t>
      <t> Then there is the class of high-speed protocols which use variances in  
          RTT as a congestion indicator (e.g., [AFRICA,FAST]). Such delay-based  
          approaches are more-or-less derived from the seminal work of TCP-Vegas  
          [VEGAS]. An increase in RTT is considered an early indicator of  
          congestion, and the sending rate is reduced to avoid buffer overflow. The 
          problem in this approach comes when delay-based and loss-based flows 
          share the same bottleneck link. While the delay-based flows respond to 
          increases in RTT by cutting its sending rate, the loss-based flows 
          continue to increase their sending rate. As a result a delay-based flow 
          obtains far less bandwidth than its fair share. This weakness is hard to 
          remedy for purely delay-based approaches.  
      </t>
      <t> The design of Compound TCP is to satisfy the efficiency requirement and  
          the TCP friendliness requirement simultaneously. The key idea is that  
          if the link is under-utilized, the high-speed protocol should be  
          aggressive and increase the sending rate quickly. However, once the  
          link is fully utilized, being aggressive will not only adversely affect  
          standard TCP flows but will also cause instability. As noted above,  
          delay-based approaches already have the nice property of adjusting  
          aggressiveness based on the link utilization, which is observed by the  
          end-systems as an increase in RTT. CTCP incorporates a scalable delay- 
          based component into the standard TCP's congestion avoidance algorithm.  
          Using the delay component as an automatic tuning knob, CTCP is scalable  
          yet TCP friendly.  
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology" anchor="term">
      <t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
           
    <section title='IANA Considerations'>
      <t> There are no IANA considerations regarding this proposal.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title='Acknowledgements'>
      <t> Blah, blah, blah.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title='Normative References'>
      &rfc2119;
    </references>
    <references title='Informative References'>
      &rfc2581;
      &rfc3649;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
